Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, we pick up on ל״ב ע״ב lamed
bet amud bet at the very top.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rebbe Elazar, so we have just been having
a whole extensive discussion about models of תפילה tefillah and not only
in terms of halakhic issues, but also in terms of like what
it means to stand before God in prayer. So we read extensively
yesterday, we discussed חנה, Chanah, then we discussed משה, Moshe, and what
was I think stood out from both of them was a sense
of real not just like complete, you know, self-abnegation and
subjection, it was really this sort of assertive approach to God in
prayer which was quite striking. So now let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes. So the גמרא Gemara is here on the top of
ל״ב ע״ב lamed bet amud bet says the following. אמר רבי אלעזר
Amar Rebbe Elazar says Rebbe Elazar: גדולה תפילה יותר ממעשים טובים. Gedolah
tefillah yoter mi-ma'asim tovim. So now we are speaking in the sort
of praise and importance of prayer. Greater is prayer than good deeds.
שאין לך גדול ממעשים טובים יותר ממשה רבינו, She-ein lekha gadol mi-ma'asim
tovim yoter mi-Moshe Rabbeinu, for as much as yesterday we were speaking
about משה's Moshe prayer interceding on behalf of בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael,
there is nobody who is greater in their good deeds than משה
רבינו, Moshe Rabbeinu, I mean look what he did for בני ישראל,
Bnei Yisrael, he took them out of מצרים, Mitzrayim, I mean he
did everything for them. And nevertheless, even with all that he had
accomplished, אף על פי כן לא נענה אלא בתפילה, af al pi
khen lo ne'eneh ela bi-tfillah, he was only answered in prayer. שנאמר:
Shene'emar: אל תוסף דבר אלי, al tosef daber elai, do not speak
to me no more and this is when משה Moshe was praying
in order to enter into the land of Israel at the end
in the beginning of דברים Devarim at the end of the forty
years. וסמוך ליה: Vesamukh leh: עלה ראש הפסגה, aleh rosh hapisgah, and
this I'll do for you, go up to the head of the
mountain and I'll show you the entire land but I won't let
you in. It's quite interesting that this is the example about how
משה Moshe is answered in prayer because he didn't get what he
wanted, he wanted to go into the land, he was answered partly
at least,
but it seems that the גמרא Gemara is picking on this because
to say that he was answered when he interceded on behalf of
בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, which is where it's more obvious that he's
answered, but there it's not something he's given like for his sake.
Whereas here, entering into the land of Israel, what he was asking
for, he was asking for something for himself. So you might think
that he, what you know, he deserves what's coming for himself based
on everything he's accomplished. Why would he need to pray? It's something
that he's earned and that he deserves. And nevertheless, even this partial
concession that God made, God made for him only after prayer. Now
תוספות Tosafos makes an important qualification about this. תוספות Tosafos says, if
you look at תוספות: Tosafos: גדולה תפילה יותר ממעשים טובים, Gedolah tefillah
yoter mi-ma'asim tovim, says תוספות, Tosafos, בלא תפילה. be-lo tefillah. It's prayer
with your good deeds is better than your good deeds without you
know your good deeds plus your prayer is better than just your
good deeds without the prayer. שהרי משה רבינו עליו השלום אף על
פי שהיו בידו מעשים טובים הוצרך לתפילה. She-harei Moshe Rabbeinu alav hashalom
af al pi she-hayu biyado ma'asim tovim hutsrakh li-tfillah. Not to get
with the misunderstanding that you can go ahead and be a רשע
rasha and do terrible things in your life or do nothing but
if you pray well then that's better than spending your life in
מעשים טובים ma'asim tovim in good deeds. Now you know again that
obviously makes an enormous amount of sense and it's true in context
but one wonders rhetorically whether that was exactly the point of the
גמרא, Gemara, you know sometimes the גמרא Gemara does for rhetorical purposes
make you know exaggerated statements in order to emphasize how powerful or
you know something is. But תוספות Tosafos does not want you to
be misled to think that you could lead a life of not
doing good deeds and you know pray, having the
ritual—right. And as long as you pray well, God only cares for
your prayers, God doesn't care for your deeds. Right, that would be
a real, you know, perversion of obviously the values here, yeah.
Might this be a response to some Christian ideas that as long
as you repent the day before you die everything else doesn't matter
sort of to say that this actually might that this actually might
not be quite enough?
I'm not sure I see that here, I mean I don't see
the issue about repentance here and yeah.
But someone's a רשע rasha and then prays on their deathbed essentially.
Yeah but I think it seems a stretch, doesn't seem to be
the point here. All right, so now, but let's compare these, let's
bring these statements together. That's about תפילה tefillah greater than good deeds.
Now. אמר רבי אלעזר: Amar Rebbe Elazar: גדולה תענית יותר מן הצדקה.
Gedolah ta'anit yoter min hatzedakah. Right, that sounds to be like the
opposite of a message of some of the נביאים, Nevi'im, but greater
is the fast than the actual צדקה, tzedakah, than the giving of
you know of money to the poor. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? זה
בגופו וזה בממונו. Zeh begufo vezeh bemamono. When you fast you're doing
something about your body, you're you know sort of withholding, denying your
body, and when you're giving צדקה tzedakah you're just giving your money.
Now it's important to consider that there's other גמרות Gemaras that compare
things זה בגופו וזה בממונו, zeh begufo vezeh bemamono, but that's normally
comparing צדקה tzedakah to גמילות חסדים. gemilut chasadim.
That's one thing to help somebody by just writing a check, זה
בממונו, zeh bemamono, and it's another thing to help somebody with really
contributing your own efforts, גמילות חסדים, gemilut chasadim, you know and that
you actually give of yourself not just of your money. But that's
actually helping somebody else. Here it's that well one is I give
money and the other is I give up my body, I like
you know we had a גמרא Gemara before, you know my my
blood, my fat, my whatever is like given over because of the
fast, right, that those things sort of are you know are lessened
because of the fast which again really is problem, I you know
I'm I... really struggle with this. It ritualizes צדקה. Tzedakah. Like the
whole value of צדקה Tzedakah is that you gave something. So better
to give your body than to give צדקה, Tzedakah, even though צדקה
Tzedakah in fact can be helping somebody and תענית Taanis is a
ritual act and it shows your commitment and it shows maybe your
serving of God but it's not something that's doing something for somebody
else. And you know if you think about the נביאים, Nevi'im, the
נביאים Nevi'im say, right what do they say about the fast day?
They say why do I need your fasts? What I need you
to do is I need you to care, clothe the naked and
feed the hungry, right? So it's quite striking in contrast to that.
Maybe reading it in a very narrow sense, similar to the מעשים
טובים, Maasim Tovim, what it means
is that if you want to be answered in your prayer because
תענית Taanis was very much in the context of there wasn't rain
and we needed rain and we needed to be answered and we
needed the rain and it was a form of a type of
a prayer if you want. And you know we say תפילה תשובה
צדקה מעבירין את רוע הגזירה, Tefillah Teshuvah Tzedakah Maavirin Es Roa HaGezeirah,
so maybe in that mode don't think that you're answered just by
giving some money to the poor. In that mode what's required also
is to show you're really doing something in terms of
extending yourself and prepared to suffer and so on. So maybe to
interpret this in a more narrow sense but reading it more broadly
it's very disturbing obviously. Yes.
Did the כהנים Kohanim feel a particular obligation to give of themselves
to the poor and needy beyond what they did in the בית
המקדש?
Beis HaMikdash? I don't know about giving to the poor and the
needy but there's a famous משנה Mishnah that says that the כהנים
Kohanim thought that they were exempt from giving the שקל Shekel because
they figured we work here we don't have to pay the dues.
So there is a משנה Mishnah about that which is quite interesting
in terms of that psychology. So obviously at least in that way
it was. All right anyway that's the statement here but again as
I said it is challenging. Let's see the next statement of ר'
אלעזר, Rebbi Elazar, a couple of parallel statements. Yes.
Ah well okay but again that's not what's being said but that's
a way of dealing with it, right? Okay
so one minute let
me just check what the מהרש"א Maharsha says.
Yeah all right, all right so let's keep on going. The מהרש"א
Maharsha reminds us that there was an earlier גמרא Gemara on ו'
עמוד ב' Vav Amud Beis that said אגרא דתעניתא צדקתא Agra D’Taanisa
Tzidkasa which also said the exact opposite, that said the reward of
a fast day is the money you give on the fast day.
So again it's interesting that this statement goes against on the face
of it a number of other statements. ויאמר רבי אלעזר גדולה תפילה
יותר מן הקרבנות. Vayomer Rebbi Elazar Gedolah Tefillah Yoser Min HaKorbanos. Prayer
is greater than sacrifices. Now that's important obviously in terms of the
whole theme that we've been discussing for a while here. שנאמר למה
לי רוב זבחיכם. Shene’emar Lama Li Rov Zivcheichem. Why do I need
all your sacrifices? וכתיב ובפרישכם כפיכם U’Kesiv U’Vefarishchem Kapeichem when you stretch
out your hands I don't answer you in prayer. So after God
said I don't need your sacrifices there was still a הוה אמינא
Hava Amina possibility he would have answered us in prayer and the
next פסוק Pasuk says no. Again that's a that's in a time
when response to sin. But the point is that there was a
possibility that prayer would have been answered more than sacrifices.
Okay. אמר
רבי יוחנן כל כהן שהרג את הנפש. Amar Rebbi Yochanan Kol Kohen
Sheharag Es HaNefesh. Now that we've quoted this פסוק, Pasuk, thank you,
we have a little digression. Any כהן Kohen that has committed murder
לא ישא כפיו Lo Yisa Kapav cannot cannot do ברכת כהנים, Birkas
Kohanim, lift up his hands. שנאמר ידיכם דמים מלאו. Shene’emar Yedeichem Damim
Maleu. Your hands are filled with blood is the end of that
verse. And so if hands are filled with blood how can the
same hands that have taken a life actually be used in ברכת
כהנים? Birkas Kohanim? There's actually some questions about cases, tragic cases where
somebody accidentally killed somebody, his wagon ran over somebody or so on,
can they do תשובה? Teshuvah? In terms of can they then be
a כהן Kohen to do נשיאת כפיים. Nesias Kapayim. So this is
learned from this פסוק. Pasuk. All right but anyway we have stringing
together a number of statements of ר' אלעזר. Rebbi Elazar. So it's
quite fascinating that the same ר' אלעזר Rebbi Elazar who talks about
the power of prayer greater than that of קרבנות Korbanos and the
power of prayer in terms of משה Moshe interceding, again has this
issue about תענית Taanis more than צדקה. Tzedakah. I'm trying to sort
of figure out how that fits into not משה Moshe interceding but
משה Moshe being answered in his prayer not מעשים טובים. Maasim Tovim.
And if you put those together, right it really does seem that
if you string those together it's really taking תוספות'ס Tosafos’s qualification out
of the picture. It seems like it's really saying that how we
sort of connect to God through our prayers, through our fasts, the
fasting is a way of connecting to God is greater than the
deeds that we do here, the deeds of whether we're giving צדקה
Tzedakah or whether we're giving מעשים טובים, Maasim Tovim, right? So again
that's a little bit it's a little disturbing if you sort of
take that at its face value. All right so now the גמרא
Gemara continues.
Not necessarily. Sometimes they use rhetorically right. It's like you know right
now if I'm... Trying to get you to work on your דאוונינג
*davening*, I'm going to tell you תפילה Tfillah, *tefillah* is more important
than מעשים טובים massim tovim? *maasim tovim*. And next week when I'm
trying to get you work on your מעשים טובים *maasim tovim*, I'm
going to tell you exactly! There could be.
But the challenge is to figure out and conceptualize the intersection between
the two, like how they're related to each other. Like the whole
thing is relational, it sounds like he's saying, right? In other words,
if two people can be employer/employee and the employee can behave in
a stellar way, but if there is no acknowledgment that is verbalized,
in some ways the meaning of that behavior remains dormant. There's no
activating of the relationship between the two. It's got to be put
into words.
So that's what you mean, the מעשים טובים *maasim tovim* then becomes
with תפילה *tefillah*, but reading it with תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* said that
it's the מעשים טובים *maasim tovim* that then have the תפילה *tefillah*,
right, because that actually, as you said very beautifully, articulates the relationship
and it's not just the deed. And that's correct also because one
to add to that is the מעשים טובים *maasim tovim* or the
צדקה *tzedakah*, you know, you could do those things just because you're
a good guy. They don't have to be in a religious context.
They don't have to be about your, as you said, about your
relationship with God. So the תפילה *tefillah* or if you would, the
תענית ta'anit *taanit*, if you assume that that's added in addition to
them, not instead of them, you know, it expresses them within a
God relationship. So yes, very nicely said point.
Maybe we'll mention this quite minutely. But you know, with this idea
that משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu *Moshe Rabbeinu* was the greatest, I guess,
doing מעשים טובים *maasim tovim*, usually we think about it in the
context of, you know, חסד *chesed* and so on. But I don't
think so. I think the context of, you know, I mean he
was a national liberator.
Right. Well, that is what I said. Right. The מעשים טובים *maasim
tovim* normally we think of it in a very sort of at
a very private level, right, but מעשים *maasim*, but you know, somebody
who takes בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael. *Bnei Yisrael* out, that's pretty good
in the מעשים טובים *maasim tovim* department, right? So okay. דאמר רבי
Rebbe, אלעזר מיום שחרב בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *De'amar Rabbi Elazar mi-yom
she-charav Beit Ha-Mikdash*. Now the same רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* who a
minute ago said that תפילה *tefillah* was better than קרבנות *korbanot*. Let's
see what he says here. From the day that the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash. *Beit Ha-Mikdash* was destroyed, ננעלו שערי תפילה *nin'alu sha'arei tefillah*,
the gates of תפילה *tefillah* have been locked.
So that's interesting, especially since he just a minute ago praised תפילה
*tefillah* over קרבנות *korbanot*. שנאמר shene'emar, גם כי אזעק ואשווע סתם תפלתי
*Shene'emar gam ki ez'ak va-ashave'a satam tefillati*. Even if I cry out
and you know, pray or whatever call out, my prayers have been
stopped up, have been sealed. ואף על פי כן *Ve-af al pi
ken*, which is by איכה *Eichah*, right after the חורבן הבית Churban
Habayit *Churban Ha-Bayit*. ואף על פי ששערי תפילה ננעלו *Ve-af al pi
she-sha'arei tefillah nin'alu*, although the gates of prayer have been locked, שערי
דמעה לא ננעלו *sha'arei dima lo nin'alu*, the gates of tears have
not been locked. שנאמר shene'emar שמעה תפלתי ה׳ ושועתי האזינה *Shene'emar shma
tefillati Hashem ve-shavati ha'azina*. Hear my prayer, God, hear my calling out,
give ear to my calling out, אל דמעתי אל תחרש *el dimati
al techerash*. To my tears do not be silent. So even after,
so the way רש״י Rashi *Rashi* explains it, it's not only what
comes after the prayer, but the fact is is to not be
silent means that you've already heard them and you're not—so don't turn
a deaf ear means as opposed to, you know, the first part
of it was first listen. But to turn a deaf ear means
to some degree you've already heard and don't ignore them. So you
see that the prayer—that the tears get in further than just the
prayer. So again this is quite interesting, right, because he says maybe
the even when it comes to תפילה *tefillah*, even if תפילה *tefillah*
is greater than קרבנות *korbanot*, but the fact that there's a בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash, *Beit Ha-Mikdash* is not just about קרבנות *korbanot*, it's
about God's presence among the people and our—the nature of our relationship.
So if there's no בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash, *Beit Ha-Mikdash* and the
nature of our relationship is such that means that God is more
distant even when it comes to prayer, not just—it doesn't have an
impact just in terms of the קרבנות *korbanot*. You know it's an
interesting thing because when we have like a תשעה באב *Tisha B'Av*,
I think a lot of people struggle like what does this mean,
how do I relate to this idea of no בית המקדש *Beit
Ha-Mikdash*, you know, you know, is it I'm—you know, how do I—that
there's no animal sacrifices, is that something that I can relate to?
But you—and often there's an attempt to sort of address that is
to think about what it means in terms of our relationship with
God and, you know, and when there was that בית המקדש *Beit
Ha-Mikdash* besides the animal sacrifices what that meant in terms of the
intimacy in a society in connection with God. So here although he's
saying that it's greater than קרבנות *korbanot*, it has an impact on
other things, you know, the חורבן הבית Churban Habayit *Churban Ha-Bayit* has
an impact on the prayer as well. In terms of the tears,
one would imagine that that's a degree to which one, you know,
has really, you know, is
a—how much one is really sort of, you know, feels bad and
is really striving to connect to God and also touches on the
issue here as well, I would imagine, the issue of the sincerity
which we've been talking about as well. And how profound is this,
you know, one's prayer. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues,
רבא לא גזר תעניתא ביומא דעיבא *Rava lo gazar taanita be-yoma de-eiva*.
This is also like a parenthetical statement. רבא *Rava* would not make
a fast day on a day of clouds, משום שנאמר shene'emar סכותה
בענן לך מעבור תפלה *mishum shene'emar sakota be-anan lach me-avor tefillah*. Since
we are quoting איכה *Eichah*, you have covered yourself over with a
cloud from hearing prayer. So when there's a cloud, that's not—that's some
symbolic that God is dividing God's self from us and that the
prayer would not be accepted. Of course given that it might rain.
Given that you're praying for rain, one wonders why you're not praying
when it's cloudy, as if maybe you don't need to. Okay, I
don't know.
You're about to receive some.
What? Well right, and that's the next line we're going to get
to. אמר רבי אלעזר מיום שחרב בית המקדש נפסקה חומת ברזל בין
ישראל לאביהם שבשמיים. Miyom she-charav Beit HaMikdash nifsaka chomat barzel bein Yisrael
le-avihem she-bashamayim. From the time that the בית המקדש was destroyed, a
wall of iron separated Israel and their Father in heaven, which is
very heavy, right? It's not just that it's like—well, I mean, before
we had the gates being locked, but somehow to be divided with
a wall of iron seems much harsher. שנאמר, shene'emar as it is
said, ואתה קח לך מחבת ברזל, ve-atah kach lecha machavat barzel, take
for yourself a iron frying pan, ונתתה אותה קיר ברזל בינך ובין
העיר, ve-natatah otah kir barzel beinecha u-vein ha-ir, place it as an
iron wall between you and the city as symbolic of an iron
wall between God and בני ישראל. So again, ending on a little
bit of a down note, these
statements of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that all these things are so
great. Prayer is great and תענית is great and then speaking about
how hard it is for them to have an effect nowadays because
we're in a post חורבן churban reality.
So I'm not exactly sure what we're supposed to do with that.
It feels very paralyzed.
So what? Cry. We're supposed to cry for the
redemption, for the building of the בית המקדש.
There you go.
Correct. אמר רבי חנינא אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Chanina Amar Rabbi
Chanina כל המאריך בתפילתו. kol ha-ma'arich bi-tfilato. Now that we're talking about
prayer, the power of prayer and prayer being responded to, here's some
other statements. So anybody who goes at length in their prayer, which
maybe means spends a lot of time and has a lot of
כוונה, kavanah, or maybe it means adds to their prayer, we spoke
before about adding to your prayer, אין תפילתו חוזרת ריקם. ein tfilato
chozeret reikam.
If you really invest in it,
it will not come back to you empty-handed. You will be answered
to some degree at least. מנלן, menalan, where do you know this?
ממשה רבנו, mi-Moshe Rabbeinu, שנאמר shene'emar ואתפלל אל השם, va-etpallel el Hashem,
I prayed to God. וכתיב בתריה u-chtiv batrei וישמע השם אלי גם
בפעם ההיא, va-yishma Hashem elai gam ba-pa'am ha-hi, God also listened to
me. Now how does that prove it? Because we're missing some words
from the פסוקים, psukim, right? What's the end of the פסוק? pasuk?
How long did Moshe pray to God? ואתפלל אל השם va-etpallel el
Hashem ארבעים יום וארבעים לילה, arbaim yom ve-arbaim lailah, right?
So Moshe prayed for forty days and forty nights and then God
answered him. So is this really true? ואמר רבי חייא בר אבא
אמר רבי יוחנן ve-amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan כל
המאריך בתפילתו ומעיין בה kol ha-ma'arich bi-tfilato u-me'ayein bah סוף בא לידי
כאב לב. sof ba lidei ke'ev lev.
Anybody that you know really sort of extends their prayer and then
sort of focuses in it, like sort of as רש"י Rashi says,
you know, is sort of like you know expecting to be answered
or waiting to be answered, always going back, I דאוונד davened so
hard, where am I, you know when am I going to be
answered for it? So in the end that's going to lead to
heartache. Okay. שנאמר shene'emar תוחלת ממושכה מחלה לב. tochelet memushacha machala lev.
An extended תוחלת, tochelet, which is being read as as a prayer,
you know, could be like an anticipation, a hope, but here it's
being read as a prayer or an extended or a prayer as
a hope for a response will lead to heartache. מאי תקנתיה, mai
takantei, what do you do? יעסוק בתורה ya'asok ba-Torah learn תורה, Torah,
שנאמר shene'emar, ועץ חיים תאווה
באה. ve-etz chayim ta'avah ba'ah. The tree of life, you know, your
desire will come, so that which you desire will come if you
involve yourself in תורה. Torah. ואין עץ חיים אלא תורה ve-ein etz
chayim ela Torah the tree of life is תורה, Torah, שנאמר shene'emar,
עץ חיים היא למחזיקים בה. etz chayim hi la-machazikim bah. It is
a tree of life to those that hold fast to it. So
you see, let me just finish—so you see that, you see that
if you go a long prayer, it's going to lead to heartache.
So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult.
הא דמאריך
ומעיין בה הא דמאריך ולא מעיין בה. ha de-ma'arich u-me'ayein bah ha
de-ma'arich ve-lo me'ayein bah. Nobody's saying that a long prayer is not
going to be answered, but the question is this second qualification that
you say, 'Oh, because I דאוונד davened so hard, I'm expecting to
be answered.' Now אמר רבי חמא בר חנינא, amar Rabbi Chama bar
Chanina, let's just finish, אם ראה אדם שהתפלל ולא נענה, im ra'ah
adam she-hitpallel ve-lo na'anah, if you saw you prayed and you were
not answered, יחזור ויתפלל, yachzor ve-yitpallel, don't give up hope, go דאוון
daven again, שנאמר shene'emar, as it says קווה אל השם חזק ויאמץ
לבך וקווה אל השם. kaveh el Hashem chazak ve-yameitz libecha ve-kaveh el
Hashem.
Have hope to God and then strengthen yourself and have hope for
God again. If it didn't work, try again. So quite interesting because
the גמרא Gemara is now dealing with this issue about, you know,
are our prayers answered and how do we deal with the sense
that sometimes maybe it feels we're not answered or what do we
do in order to get them answered. So one is really work,
have a lot of כוונה. kavanah. If it's not successful the first
time, it doesn't mean that it's not going to be answered even
if you gave it your all, sometimes you have to try again
and again to really reach out and connect and so on. But
then this interesting point about oh it's just going to lead to
heartache. העוסק בתורה, ha-osek ba-Torah, but one point could be as we're
sort of most inclined to do is focus on the term of
מעיין בה me'ayein bah and say that the problem is it's like
okay you know maybe we're promising that you'll be answered but you
sort of undermine it if you expect to be answered. It's like
you know the story about the גמרא Gemara says that you know
anybody that runs away from כבוד, kavod, כבוד kavod will run after
him. So a guy goes to the rabbi and says, 'You know,
all my life I've been running away from כבוד kavod and כבוד
kavod has never run after me.'
He says, 'Were you looking behind yourself as you were running away
to get?' So anyway so okay it'll be. answered, but if you're
expecting it to be answered, that sort of undermines. You could also
say the גמרא Gemara isn't saying that it won't be answered if
you're מעיין בה, me'ayein bah, it says that it leads to heartache,
right? Is that you're just, you know, sometimes your prayers are answered
in ways you don't expect them to be, they're answered only many
years later you realize that what seemed like they weren't being answered
was a way in which your prayer was answered. So maybe it's
very different to sort of say it will be answered, just have
confidence that it'll be answered rather than your expectations of how and
when you expect them to answer it, that will be lead to
heartache. So that's different than saying that the expectation sort of, you
know,
sort of neutralizes their effect. It doesn't necessarily neutralize their effect, but
it just, you know, it might just lead to a lot of
heartache because of what you have in going on in your head.
But the final possibility that should be mentioned here is the issue
in general which is this possible tension between prayer and תלמוד תורה.
Talmud Torah. Because the more time you take in prayer, the time
you take away from תלמוד תורה. Talmud Torah. This is about המאריך
בתפילה, hamarich bitfillah, you're not just to fulfill your obligation. And it
could be, although the גמרא Gemara. doesn't frame it this way, רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is saying, you know what? If you want your,
you know, your prayers to be answered, you should spend your time
sitting in the בית מדרש Beis Medrash and learning, בעוסק בתורה. beoseik
batorah. Don't spend, you know, so much time in prayer. You do
your דאוון, daven, you ask God what you need to ask God
for and then you go and sit and learn and that's a
better way to spend your time than being מאריך בתפילה marich bitfillah
and then it's less about the מעיין בה me'ayein bah as the
question about the מאריך, marich, what are you spending your time doing?
Exactly.
To me, the answer to all this question of does השם Hashem
answer prayer or what if we have to wait is symbolized in
חנה Channah who obviously when she was standing at the temple, that
was not the first time she prayed, the first time was obvious,
right, and then עלי Eli recognized her.
Right, she obviously had waited a very long time, never gave up
and continued to pray even deeper and more deeply. Right. So I
think that that should be our
right and it's so and that's exactly the end of the second
line of the גמרא. Gemara It's not just you gave a long,
long prayer, but it's that you keep on praying and you keep
on sort of right, you know, and that reaffirmation also of the
faith that's implicit in prayer is something that you know, if you
pray once and expect to be answered, it's like, you know, you
know, it's like okay, I asked for it, I should get it.
But if you keep on praying then it also says something very
powerful about that, you know, faith and the relationship. Absolutely, yes. Getting
a ברכה bracha from the רבי, definitely. Ha, right, yeah.
Maybe God answers prayers but maybe
sometimes the answer is no.
That's also the case, right.
Like משה רבינו trying to get in.
Exactly, exactly, right. That's right, exactly. All prayers are answered, sometimes the
answer is no, exactly.
Okay, so let's let's see now how's the גמרא Gemara, continues. תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, ארבעה צריכים חיזוק, arba’ah tzrichim chizuk,
four things need to be reinforced. Okay, don't come easily, you need
to work on them again and again and they need to be
reinforced. ואלו הן, ve'eilu hein, תורה, Torah, okay, to be, you know,
to make gains in תורה, Torah, you need constantly to reinforce yourself,
it's not easy to sustain it. ומעשים טובים, umassim tovim, doing good
deeds in the world.
תפילה, prayer, ודרך ארץ, vederech eretz, and דרך ארץ derech eretz which
here basically means a like רש״י Rashi says a פרנסה, parnassah, a
job. You know, making a go of a living, of making a
living in life.
ארץ, תורה, ומעשים טובים מניין, Eretz, Torah, umassim tovim minayin, how do
you know תורה Torah and מעשים טובים? שנאמר, shene'emar, רק חזק ואמץ
מאד, rak chazak ve'ematz me'od, only strengthen yourself and be very strong.
לשמור ולעשות, lishmor vela'asos, to do it, to observe,
לשמור ולעשות ככל התורה, lishmor vela'asos kechol hatorah, all this
תורה. Torah. חזק בתורה, chazak batorah, strengthen yourself in learning תורה, Torah,
ואמץ ve'ematz and again strengthen yourself במעשים טובים bemassim tovim in good
deeds. And probably it's also like לשמור ולעשות, lishmor vela'asos, לעשות la'asos
is the doing, לשמור lishmor observing but it could also mean the
knowing in order to do. So if you want to, you know,
make accomplishments in תורה, Torah, even if you want to do a
life of contributing to the world, to the Jewish community, it doesn't,
you know, there's a lot of frustrations that'll become your way and
a lot of a lot of stumbling and you need constant reinforcement
and constant strength. תפילה מניין, Tfillah minayin, שנאמר, קוה אל ה׳ חזק
ויאמץ לבך וקוה אל ה׳. kaveh el Hashem chazak veya'ametz libecha vekaveh
el Hashem. You sort of you know, you reach out to God,
you hope to God and and your heart needs to be strengthened
and you need to do it yet again.
דרך ארץ מניין, Derech eretz minayin, how do you know דרך ארץ?
derech eretz? שנאמר, חזק ונתחזק בעד
עמנו, chazak venischazek be'ad ameinu, strong and be strengthened for the sake
of our people. So it's interesting there the sense of דרך ארץ
derech eretz that בעד עמנו be'ad ameinu but רש״י Rashi, says if
you look at רש״י, Rashi רש״י Rashi translates it very broadly. רש״י
Rashi? says where's the רש״י? Rashi דרך
ארץ אם אומן הוא לאומנותו אם סוחר הוא לסחורתו אם איש מלחמה
הוא למלחמתו. derech eretz im uman hu l’umanuso im socher hu l’schoraso
im ish milchama hu l’milchamaso. So whatever your job is, you know,
it's a profession, you know, it's not always easy to be successful
one's profession and requires a lot of a lot of reinforcement and
strength. Okay. ותאמר ציון עזבני ה׳ וה׳ שכחני. vatomer Tzion azavani Hashem
vaHashem shichechani. Zion has said God has abandoned me and God has
forgotten me. היינו עזובה והיינו שכוחה. hainu azuvah vehainu shichuchah. So abandoned
and forgotten is essentially the same, what's the double language? אמר ריש
לקיש, amar Reish Lakish, אמרה כנסת ישראל לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא, amrah
knesses Yisrael lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, the Jewish people said before the
Holy One Blessed be He. Master of universe. אדם נושא אשה על
אשתו ראשונה. Adam nosei isha al ishto rishona. So if a man
marries a woman after his first wife, זוכר מעשה ראשונה. Zocher maaseh
rishona. So at least he'll remember even if this is a second
wife, he remembers his first wife, he remembers special times they had
together. אתה עזבתני, Ata azavtani, you have abandoned me, ושכחתני ushechachtani
and you've forgotten me. You don't even think about me anymore. It's
not enough that there's no longer בית המקדש, whatever, but it's not
just you left me, it's like you've completely forgotten me. אמר לו
הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu, so God said, בתי,
Biti, my daughter, י״ב מזלות בראתי ברקיע, Yud-Beit mazalot barati barakia, I've
created twelve constellations in the heaven. ועל כל מזל ומזל בראתי לו
שלשים חיל, Ve'al kol mazal umazal barati lo sheloshim chayil, of every
constellation there is thirty troops, ועל כל חיל וחיל בראתי לו שלשים
לגיון, ve'al kol chayil vechayil barati lo sheloshim ligyon, or thirty armies,
every army has
thirty legions, ועל כל לגיון ולגיון בראתי לו שלשים רהטון, ve'al kol
ligyon veligyon barati lo sheloshim rhaton, thirty I don't know what רהטון
rhaton is, different types of officer, a certain army officer, ועל כל
רהטון ורהטון בראתי לו שלשים קרטון, ve'al kol rhaton verhaton barati lo
sheloshim karton, another type of colonel, general, ועל כל קרטון וקרטון בראתי
לו שלשים גסטרא, ve'al kol karton vekarton barati lo sheloshim gistra, yet
another I don't know, a lieutenants for every colonel, ועל כל גסטרא
וגסטרא תליתי בו שלש מאות וששים וחמשה אלפי ריבוא כוכבים, ve'al kol
gistra vegistra taliti bo shelosh me'ot veshishim vachamisha alfei ribo kochavim, and
for every one of those I have made, I have hung on
them three hundred and sixty-five thousand
ten thousand. So that is three hundred and sixty-five ten millions. So
that's what, 3.650... I don't know, 3 billion 650
million, I think I did the right math,
stars כנגד ימות החמה, keneged yemot hachamah, equivalent to the days of
the solar year times ten billion or something. Okay. וכולם לא בראתי
אלא בשבילך, Vekulam lo barati ela bishvilech, all of these things, now
actually you know if you think about how many galaxies and stars
are, how many stars are there supposed to be in the galaxy,
do we know? Trillions. Trillions, right? So you read this גמרא, Gemara
it seems like a crazy exaggeration, but really it's, you know, in
terms of the number of stars. Okay, anyway, so there are trillions
of stars.
Anyway, so where are we? וכולם לא בראתי אלא בשבילך, Vekulam lo
barati ela bishvilech, all of this is for you, for כלל ישראל.
Klal Yisrael. ואת אמרת עזבתני ושכחתני? Veat amart azavtani ushechachtani? You think
I've abandoned you and forgotten you? התשכח אשה עולה? Hatishkach isha olah?
אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu, כלום אשכח עולות אילים,
Klum eshkach olot eilim, hearing עולה olah as an עולה, olah, do
you think I'll ever forget the rams of the sacrifices you brought
for me? ופטרי רחמים, Upitrei rachamim, and the פטרי רחם, petrei rechem,
the firstborn, you know, animals, שהקרבת לפני במדבר, shehikravat lefanai bamidbar, that
you brought before me in the מדבר? midbar? אמרה לפניו, Amrah lefanav,
so כנסת ישראל Knesset Yisrael said to God, רבונו של עולם, Ribono
Shel Olam, הואיל ואין שכחה לפני כסא כבודך, Hoil ve'ein shikcha lifnei
kisei kvodecha, since there's no forgetfulness, right, that's a line actually you
might remember from the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei of ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, אין שכחה לפני כסא כבודך. Ein shikcha lifnei kisei kvodecha. Anyway,
since there's no forgetfulness before your holy throne, שמא לא תשכח לי
מעשה העגל? Shema lo tishkach li maaseh ha'egel? So there are actually
some things I'd like you to forget.
Maybe you won't forget for me, you know, the sin of the
golden calf, and I'm going to be punished for those still? אמר
לה, Amar lah, so God said to her, גם אלה תשכחנה, Gam
eileh tishkachnah, even these I will forget.
אמרה לפניו, Amrah lefanav, רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, הואיל ויש
שכחה לפני כסא כבודך, Hoil veyesh shikcha lifnei kisei kvodecha, since you
are going to forget certain things, שמא תשכח לי מעשה סיני? Shema
tishkach li maaseh Sinai? Maybe you'll forget for me the good stuff,
like when I stood
at הר סיני? Har Sinai? אמר לה, Amar lah, God said, ואנכי
לא אשכחך, Ve'anochi lo eshkachech, I will not forget you. Now רש״י
points out that this is actually embedded in the words.
גם אלה תשכחנה, Gam eileh tishkachnah, I'll forget אלה, eileh, אלה אלהיך
ישראל, Eileh elokecha Yisrael, but ואנכי, Ve'anochi, אנכי ה' אלהיך, Anochi Hashem
Elokecha, לא אשכחך, Lo eshkachech, that experience I won't forget. And so
והיינו דאמר רבי אלעזר אמר רבי אושעיא, Vehainu de'amar Rabbi Elazar amar
Rabbi Oshaya, מאי דכתיב, Mai dichteiv, גם אלה תשכחנה, Gam eileh tishkachnah,
זה מעשה העגל. Ze maaseh ha'egel. ואנכי לא אשכחך, Ve'anochi lo eshkachech,
זה מעשה סיני, Ze maaseh Sinai, those are the doings of Sinai.
So it's interesting, one thinks, you know, if you put this in
juxtaposition to the earlier statement that after the חורבן הבית there's this
iron wall and the gates are locked. So here it is, you
know, this is obviously from the שבעה דנחמתא, Shivta d'Nechemta, very appropriate
now, you know,
that okay, even after the חורבן הבית God doesn't forget us. God,
the whole universe is created for us and God still... God is
still close to us.
Okay. So the positive dimensions of relationships that end.
Exactly, oh that's a nice point too. Yeah.
One tends to remember the positive dimensions of many relationships when the
relationships end.
Depends how they end. Not...
I don't mean that absolutely. Right, right. But there is an inclination...
right...
unless there was a tremendous amount of pain... right... and gruesomely...
right... to remember the good...
right... to highlight the positive dimensions or the way in which a
relationship was nourishing.
Right. Thank you, that's beautiful... beautifully said. Okay. So now we turn
back to the משנה mishnah which
says חסידים הראשונים, Chasidim harishonim, so... we talk go to the משנה
Mishnah which speaks about כוונה, kavana, back to the כוונה kavana issue
that the early righteous people would wait an hour before they prayed
and they would spend an hour in prayer.
who were they talking about?
who was it? חסידים ראשונים? Chasidim Rishonim? well, there was certainly a
group called חסידים Chasidim at the time of the of the Maccabees,
which were like, you know, these pietistic Jews that were also like
very not involved in the, you know, in the larger society in
the sense that like... Essenes? no, no.
the ones who refused to fight on שבת.
Shabbat. they refused, they refused to fight on שבת. Shabbat. and right,
they were annihilated. I don't know. but they also, I mean, they
also primarily didn't join with the חשמונאים Chashmonaim because they figured if
God wants it, a בית המקדש, God'll bring it down from heaven,
you know. so they were very sort of, you know,
removed, you know, sort of what's the word like cloistered type of
pietists. right, if I don't know if it's referring to those in
the as a sect or it's just referring to that there were
pious people who used to be so pious that they would spend
an hour in preparation of prayer. so it's not exactly clear what,
you know, exactly is referred to by חסידים הראשונים, Chasidim HaRishonim, but
it's not it's not it.
well, that's much, much later, חסידים, Chasidim, right. right. okay. so let's
take a look. חסידים הראשונים היו שוהים שעה אחת. Chasidim HaRishonim hayu
shohim sha'ah achat. מנא הני מילי, Minan hami li, where do we
know this from? אמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, Amar Rabi Yehoshua ben
Levi, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse
says, אשרי יושבי ביתך, Ashrei yoshvei veisecha, and then עוד יהללוך סלה.
od yehaleluha selah. first you sit and then you praise God. so
you have to be אשרי יושבי ביתך Ashrei yoshvei veisecha first. ואמר
רבי יהושע בן לוי, Ve'amar Rabi Yehoshua ben Levi, המתפלל צריך לישהות
שעה אחת אחר תפלתו. hamitpalel tzarich lish'oh sha'ah achat achar tefilato.
it's not only an hour before, it's even an hour after you
have to sit and wait. שנאמר, אך צדיקים יודו לשמך ישבו ישרים
את פניך. ach tzadikim yodu lishmecha yeshvu yesharim et panecha. either the
righteous will give thanks or acknowledgement to your name, ישבו ישרים את
פניך, yeshvu yesharim et panecha, they will sit in your presence. so
after you give the praise, then you sit. you don't run out.
like, God, please give me this, goodbye. okay, sorry I had to
run, goodbye. so, you know, you spend time afterwards. it's about also
the relationship. so part of the relationship is the verbalized part, it's
the request, but part of the relationship is just sort of the
being in the presence. so it's not just a
כוונה kavana issue, it's about that experience of being in the presence
of God. so the גמרא Gemara says,
תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly, המתפלל צריך שישהא
שעה אחת קודם תפלתו, hamitpalel tzarich sheyish'oh sha'ah achat kodem tefilato, you
have to wait an hour, again what it means שעה sha'ah literally,
the גמרא Gemara will explain it literally, understand it literally in a
minute, but an hour before one's prayer, ושעה אחת אחר תפלתו, vesha'ah
achat achar tefilato, and an hour
after. קודם תפלתו מנין שנאמר אשרי יושבי ביתך, Kodem tefilato minayin shene'emar
Ashrei yoshvei veisecha, ואחר תפלתו מנין דכתיב אך צדיקים יודו לשמך ישבו
ישרים את פניך. ve'achar tefilato minayin dechsiv ach tzadikim yodu lishmecha yeshvu
yesharim et panecha. תוספות points out that this is why we
say אשרי יושבי ביתך, Ashrei yoshvei veisecha, not תהלה לדוד. Tehillah leDavid.
תהלה לדוד Tehillah leDavid is the actual, you know, פרק perek in
תהלים, Tehillim, and that's because the גמרא Gemara says if you say
תהלה לדוד Tehillah leDavid three times a day, you're a בן עולם
הבא. ben Olam HaBa. but why do we start with the פסוקים
pesukim of תהלה לדוד, Tehillah leDavid, אשרי יושבי ביתך? Ashrei yoshvei veisecha?
and so we do it at מנחה Mincha because מנחה Mincha in
particular is where we have just a שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, right?
that's the אשרי Ashrei got added later. so the reason the אשרי
Ashrei got added to the תהלה לדוד Tehillah leDavid added later as
a way of getting us in the right mindset, preparing us and
so on. and the reason we start with אשרי יושבי ביתך Ashrei
yoshvei veisecha is because from there we learn this idea that you
don't jump right into דאבנינג. davening. you have to spend time sitting,
preparing and so on.
right, learning דף יומי. Daf Yomi. so now the גמרא Gemara says,
right, okay. תנו רבנן, Tano rabanan, we
taught similarly, חסידים הראשונים היו שוהים שעה אחת ומתפללים שעה אחת וחוזרים
ושוהים שעה אחת. Chasidim HaRishonim hayu shohim sha'ah achat umitpallelim sha'ah achat
vechozrim veshohim sha'ah achat. and wait an hour
afterwards. וכי מאחר ששוהים תשע שעות ביום, Vechi me'achar deshohim tesha sha'os
beyom, here we understand שעה sha'ah very literally. if they waited and
spent nine hours a day in
דאבנינג, davening, so בתפילה, betfila, תורתן היכא משתמרת, toratan heich mishtameret, first
of all, how was their תורה Torah preserved? ומלאכתן היכא נעשית, umelachtan
heich na'asit, how did their work get done?
אלא מתוך שחסידים הם, Ela mitoch shechasidim hem, because they were so
righteous, תורתן משתמרת ומלאכתן מתברכת. toratan mishtameret umelachtan mitbarechet. their תורה Torah
was preserved and their work was blessed, even though they worked, you
know, they did some what is it some day trading in the
stock market, they only spent a few hours, they made a lot
of money, and therefore they didn't have to spend that much time
in their work. now, I want to just share with you a
very powerful statement or whatever insight of the נציב, Netziv, רב נפתלי
צבי יהודה ברלין. Rav Naftali Zvi Yehuda Berlin. he says he contrasts
this line to a parallel line in the ירושלמי. Yerushalmi. ירושלמי Yerushalmi
asks the same question, but it doesn't say תורתן משתמרת, toratan mishtameret,
it says תורתן מתברכת. toratan mitbarechet. their תורה Torah was blessed as
opposed to just it was preserved. and he says that this reflects
they're not describing different phenomena, but they're taking different takes on the
same phenomenon, which
is that, okay, they didn't spend a lot of time learning, but
they were, you know, they intuited the correct הלכה, halacha, the correct
conclusion, even though they didn't spend a lot of time in their
sitting and learning. and he says that there's a difference of attitude
in between בבל Bavel and ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, that in בבל,
Bavel, there's a much greater investment in process than in the result,
the שקלא וטריא, shakla vetarya, in the creative aspects of תורה שבעל
פה. Torah shebe'al peh. so if you don't spend the time, even
if you come up with the right result You can't say
תורתם מתברכת. torasom nisbareches. תורתם, torasom, to have your תורה Torah blessed
means the process of learning the תורה. Torah. It's not just the
conclusions, but from the ירושלמי's Yerushalmi perspective, it's much more about coming
to the right conclusions. This is his take, and therefore you can
say even תורתם מתברכת torasom nisbareches the same way your work is
blessed. So long as you make a lot of money, who cares
how much time you spent in it? So he, interesting take he
has, noticing different sort of attitudes in terms of the תורה שבעל
פה Torah she-ba'al peh process of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל.
Bovel. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. אפילו המלך שואל בשלומו לא ישיבנו. afilu ha-melech shoel
b'shlomo lo yishivenu. As opposed to קריאת שמע, Krias Shema, even if
somebody, a king is asking after, welcomes you, you do not interrupt
before דאוונען. davening. Because here you're really standing before God. אמר רב
יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, לא שנו אלא למלכי ישראל. lo shanu ela
l'malchei Yisrael. That's only if it's a Jewish king, to some degree
he'll understand. אבל למלכי עכו"ם, Aval l'malchei akum, but if it's a
non-Jewish king, פוסק, posek, you better interrupt or your life is at
risk. מתיבי, Meisivei, עוסק בתפילה וראה אנס בא כנגדו וראה קרון בא
כנגדו. osek b'tefilla v'ra'ah anas ba kinegdo v'ra'ah karon ba kinegdo.
If you're דאוונען davening and you see some type of a strong
man coming against you or a wagon, לא יהא מפסיק אלא מקצר
ועולה. lo yehei mafsik ela m'katzer v'oleh.
Don't interrupt, just finish it up real quickly. So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא דאפשר לקצר. ha d'efshar l'katzer. If
you can finish it up real quickly, finish it up and then
get out of the way, but if you can't finish it up
real quickly, you interrupt. This is not יהרג ואל יעבור, yehareg v'al
ya'avor, it's finishing your דאוונען. davening. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabanan, מעשה בחסיד
אחד
שהיה מתפלל בדרך. ma'aseh b'chasid echad she-hayah mispalel baderach. Story of a
certain righteous person and again, חסיד chasid here,
who was praying in the way. ובא שר ונתן לו שלום. u'ba
sar v'nosan lo shalom. So a certain officer came and greeted him.
ולא החזיר לו שלום. v'lo hechezir lo shalom. He didn't respond to
him. המתין לו עד שיסיים תפלתו. himtin lo ad she-yesayem tefillaso. So
this officer waited till he finished. לאחר שסיים תפלתו, le-achar she-yesayem tefillaso,
אמר לו. amar lo. After he finished he said to him, ריקא,
reika, empty person, worthless person, הלא כתוב בתורתכם, halo kasuv b'soraschem, your
Torah says רק השמר לך ושמור נפשך, rak hishamer lecha u'shmor nafshecha,
that you should guard yourselves, you have to preserve your life, וכתיב
ונשמרתם מאד לנפשותיכם, u'chsiv v'nishmartem me'od l'nafshoseichem, and you should be very
careful of your own lives. So how did you do this thing?
You were risking your life. כשנתתי לך שלום למה לא החזרת לי
שלום kshe-nasati lecha shalom lamah lo hechezarta li shalom? When I welcomed
you, why did you not respond? אם הייתי חותך את ראשך בסייף,
im hayisi chosech es roshecha b'saif, if I had chopped your head
off with my sword, מי היה תובע את דמך מידי mi hayah
sove'a es damcha mi-yadi? Nobody would say I'd done anything wrong, nobody
would demand your blood. אמר לו, amar lo, so he said to
him, המתן לי עד שאפייסך בדברים. hamten li ad she-afayesecha b'devarim. Allow
me to appease you with words, allow me to respond. אמר לו,
amar lo, so he said to him, ואילו היית עומד לפני מלך
בשר ודם. v'ilu hayisa omed lifnei melech basar va-dam. Let's say you,
Mr. Officer, was standing in front of a human king. ובא חברך
ונתן לך שלום. u'ba chavercha v'nosan lecha shalom. And a pal came
and said hello to you. היית מחזיר לו hayisa mechezir lo? Would
you have responded to him? אמר לו לא. amar lo lo. He
said no. Top of ל"ג ע"ב. lamed gimmel amud beis. ואם היית
מחזיר לו, v'im hayisa mechezir lo, and if you would have responded
to him, מה היו עושים לך mah hayu osim lecha? What would
they do to you? אמר לו היו חותכים את ראשי בסייף. amar
lo hayu chochsim es roshi b'saif. They would chop my head off
with a sword. אמר לו, amar lo, והלא דברים קל וחומר. v'halo
devarim kal v'chomer. So from this we can learn a קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. ומה אתה שהיית עומד לפני מלך בשר ודם, u'mah atah
she-hayisa omed lifnei melech basar va-dam, if this is how you would
act if you were standing before a human king, שהיום כאן ומחר
בקבר, she-hayom kan u'machar b'kever, that today is here and the next
day is in the grave, כך, kach, and that's how you would
have acted, you would not have interrupted your presence, your being in
the king's presence to respond to somebody else. אני שהייתי עומד לפני
מלך מלכי המלכים הקדוש ברוך הוא, ani she-hayisi omed lifnei melech malchei
ha-melachim ha-kadosh baruch hu, I
that was standing in front of the King of Kings, God, שהוא
חי וקיים לעדי עד ולעולמי עולמים, she-hu chai v'kayam la'adei ad u'l'olmei
olamim, that is alive and
exists forever and ever, על אחת כמה וכמה, al achas kamah v'chamah,
how much more so should I not have interrupted God to respond
to you. מיד נתפייס אותו שר ונפטר אותו חסיד לביתו לשלום. miyad
nispayes oso sar v'niftar oso chasid l'veiso l'shalom.
So this officer was appeased and this חסיד chasid went home, ושלום
על ישראל. v'shalom al Yisrael. So, interesting story, it's a lovely story,
of course many times that's not going to work, and also you
even wonder about the example, why did he say if your friend
came and said hello to you? Like if I was the שר
sar I'd be very offended. What do you mean your friend? I'm
not your friend, right? Could have said like if an important person
would have come, you still wouldn't have interrupted if you're in the
presence of the king. So I don't exactly get why he gave
the example of as a friend came, a colleague came. Anyway, that's
that story. One also wonders what this חסיד chasid is doing being
מתפלל בדרך, mispalel baderach, right?
Why not just make sure you're praying in private so you reduce
the chances of being interrupted? But anyway,
maybe he had no choice. Maybe he had no choice, could be,
was he was traveling, right. Okay, so now we're going to have
another very famous story. אפילו נחש כרוך על עקיבו לא יפסיק, afilu
nachash karuch al akeivo lo yafsik,
even if there's a snake around your ankle do not interrupt. So
again, sounds like your life is at stake, but the גמרא Gemara
qualifies this. אמר רב ששת לא שנו אלא נחש. Amar Rav Sheshes
lo shanu ela nachash.
That's only a snake. אבל עקרב פוסק. aval akrav posek. But if
it's a scorpion, then you interrupt. Now maybe because not all snakes
are poisonous, but as the גמרא will indicate later, it also seems
like you're not necessarily afraid that the snake will bite. I don't
know, if it's a poisonous snake and it's around my ankle,
I'm not sure why I would see that as so different than
a scorpion. But anyway,
מתיבי, Meisivei, נפל לגוב אריות, nafal l'gov arayos, here's a
ברייתא. braisa. If somebody or if somebody fell into a pit of
lions like דניאל. Daniel. אין מעידין עליו שמת, ein meidin alav she-meit,
you don’t, you can’t testify that he definitely died so his wife
could remarry. Maybe the lions weren’t hungry. נפל לחפירה מלאה נחשים ועקרבים,
nafal le-chafirah mele’ah nechashim ve-akrabim, however if he fell into a pit
filled with snakes and scorpions, but it’s being understood to mean snakes
or scorpions, מעידין עליו שמת, meidin alav she-meit, you can testify that
he is dead because they definitely would have poisoned him, he would
have died. So you see there that if there’s a snake, you
have to assume that they’re going that they’re going to bite you
and that you can die, so why is it different than a
scorpion? So הגמרא Gemara says שאני התם shani hatam there it’s different
דאגב איצצא de-agav itstama because of the pressure you fell down, fell
on them, then they’re angry and they’re going to attack. But if
they’re just around, even presumably around your ankle, you can’t necessarily, you
know, maybe they won’t attack. אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, so
said אמר רב יצחק, Amar Rav Yitzchak, ריש תורא, reish tora, so
this is really in contrast because there it speaks about a snake
around your ankle, now we’re going to talk about something that, you
know, makes it clear that you have to take necessary precautions. Even
if you saw oxen, פוסק, posek, you interrupt your שמונה עשרה Shemoneh
Esrei and get away from the ox. You know, oxen you would
not normally assume are violent, nevertheless, you never know. So דתניא ditanya
we learned because רבי יאשיה Rebbe Yoshiyah taught מרחיקין משור תם חמשים
אמה, merachakin mishor tam chamishim amah, stay away from an ox even
if it’s never gored, חמשים אמה, chamishim amah, like you know 70
feet, 75 feet, ומשור מועד umishor muad and if it’s an ox
that has gored in the past, כמלא עיניו, kemlo einav, you can’t
even be within its eyesight. Ah, you know, don’t let it even
see you. So again now those are things which you would assume
that even if they did gore you, it’s not as life-threatening as
a poisonous snake. So again here the הגמרא Gemara is really counterbalancing
the משנה Mishnah and making it much more reasonable. No, if there’s
any serious concern of danger, take care of it. Wait, let’s read
a little more. תניא בשמיה דרבי מאיר, Tanya be-shmeih de-Rebbe Meir, we
taught in the name of רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, ריש
תורא בדיקולא, reish tora be-dikula, if the head of an ox is
in its like basket, סליק לאיגרא, salik le-igra, even if it looks
like it’s distracted and it’s eating, it’s not looking at you, it’s
not angry, nevertheless, keep away from it. סליק לאיגרא, salik le-igra, go
up to the roof, ושדי דרגא מתותך vushadi darga mitutach and kick
the ladder away from you. So okay, get away, don’t be around
oxen.
So you have to climb a climb a ladder?
It’s an exaggeration, רש"י Rashi says. Well, sure.
You know, I don’t understand why it’s so bad, like we just
said before, ושמרתם מאד לנפשותיכם. ushmartem me’od lenafshoteichem. And but anybody would
know. I understand.
I go near a bull, then
you know, you
don’t need a rabbi.
All right, sometimes people listen to it more when it’s a rabbi.
Somebody told me you know a rabbi that on ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah got up and like for the for the for the sermon
said, for the sermon said,
make sure that there are batteries in all of your like smoke
detectors in the house, that they’re checked out. I don’t know how
we would consider that as a ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah sermon, but
the point is, you know, sometimes that’s rabbi’s responsibility and you know
people listen to the rabbi to concern himself even about the health
issues of other people, you know, about safety issues if people will
listen to him. What?
Rabbis say a lot of things, and this is what’s being quoted
as a life lesson. Right. Not everything a rabbi does says
is gets quoted in the literature, so right. All right. Anyway, so
it says like this,
it shocks me because we are totally we we’ve never witnessed in
our time any non-rational behavior amongst the religious.
All right, who says this was not rational? This was a way
of, I think it’s very I think it’s very beautiful that he’s
concerned about the safety of people and he feels it’s part of
his responsibility.
It’s not so obvious to me.
Right. Right. Exactly. אמר שמואל, Amar Shmuel, הני מילי בשור שחור,
hani milei
beshor
shachor,
so now the הגמרא Gemara does treat it as like it would
treat a halachic statement, it’s analyzing it. This is only if it’s
a black ox וביומי ניסן ubeyomei nisan and it’s in the spring
מפני שהשטן מרקד בין קרניו. mipnei she-hasatan merakid bein karnav.
The Satan is dancing between its horns. Like רש"י Rashi says, you
know, it’s been the it’s been the winter now finally the sun
is shining, the grass, the flowers, it’s got some you know some
blood running through it, it’s looking for trouble. What? It’s in heat,
could
be. It could be that too. But you know like for example
the reason that there was a like a lot of a lot
of pogroms occurred in the spring. So, a, it was associated possibly
with Easter, but also you know after the thaw of the winter
people are looking for trouble, you know, they want they’ve got all
this energy and they want to sort of go out.
Okay. תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, מעשה במקום אחד שהיה ערוד והיה מזיק
את הבריות. ma'aseh bemakom echad shehayah arod vehayah mazik et habriyot. There’s
a certain place that there was an ערוד arod which is some
type of a of a scorpion-like creature. How do they translate it
there? Snake?
That’s not exactly, actually a picture of a
snake in this thing.
Yeah, well, the הגמרא Gemara okay the הגמרא Gemara has it as
some type of a cross-breed between a snake and some other reptile.
Anyway, whatever it is, some poisonous scorpion snake-like creature.
והיה מזיק את הבריות, vehayah mazik et habriyot, and it was it
was injuring people. באו והודיעו לרבי חנינא בן דוסא, Bau vehodiu le-Rabbi
Chanina ben Dosa, they told רבי חנינא בן דוסא. Rabbi Chanina ben
Dosa. אמר להם, Amar lahem, הראוני את חורו, har'uni et choro, show
me its hole. הראו לו את חורו, Her'u lo et choro, they
showed him its hole. ונתן עקבו על פי החור, Venatan akeivo al
pi hachor, he
put his heel on the mouth of the hole. like from the
משנה *Mishnah* was by the hole. יצא ונשכו ומת *Yatza venishcho vamet*.
So the scorpion snake came out, it bit him, and the scorpion
died. אותו חבר אותו חבר *Oto chavar oto chavar*, that snake. נטלו
על כתיפו *Netalo al ketefo*, he put it on his shoulder, so
to get it sounds like a snake. והביאו לבית המדרש *Vehevio le'beit
hamidrash*. He brought it to the בית מדרש *Beit Midrash*. אמר להם
*Amar lahem* and he said to them, ראו בני *Reu banai*, see
my sons. בני אין ערוד ממית אלא החטא ממית *Banai ein arod
memit ela hachet memit*, an ערוד *arod* is not what kills, but
the חטא *sin* that kills. באותה שעה *Be'otah sha'ah* they said, אוי
לו לאדם שפגע בו ערוד *Oy lo le'adam shepaga bo arod*, woe
to the person that an ערוד *arod* encounters, an ערוד *arod* encounters
an ערוד *arod*. ואוי לו לערוד *Ve'oy lo la'arod*, woe to the
ערוד *arod* שפגע בו רבי חנינא בן דוסא *shepaga bo Rabbi Chanina
ben Dosa* that runs into רבי חנינא בן דוסא *Rabbi Chanina ben
Dosa*. Now having that statement right here, okay, besides the power of
the idea about, you know, אין החטא ממית *ein hachet memit*, you
know, it's the חטא *chet* that's ממית *memit* and about like our
deeds also, you know, determine these things, is also but
having the juxtaposition also suggest like another reason you shouldn't interrupt your
דאווענינג *davening*. If you're really פרום *frum* in your דאווענינג *davening*, then
these things won't damage you. So that a little bit undercuts the
way in which the גמרא *Gemara* was counter-balancing the משנה *Mishnah*. The
משנה *Mishnah* says don't interrupt with a snake. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says snake, but there's also a scorpion, actually even if there's an
ox, you've got to stay away from it, right? And then by
having this story to end it, a little bit sort of says,
but if you're really פרום *frum* it won't hurt you. So again,
I'm not sure that that was intended, but that's a little bit
I think the message that gets conveyed.
ראו בני אין ערוד ממית
אלא החטא ממית *Reu banai ein arod memit ela hachet memit*. Right,
meaning anybody other than רבי חנינא בן דוסא *Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa*,
right? Now right, I was going to say, I was going to
say that if you look at רש"י *Rashi*, רש"י *Rashi* quotes a
בה"ג *Bahag*, the בעל הלכות גדולות *Ba'al Halachot Gedolot*, so it feels
a need to make this a little less completely miraculous. And here's
what רש"י *Rashi* says. מצאתי בהלכות גדולות *Matzati Behalachot Gedolot* עמי במערבא
*ami bema'arava* that quotes the תלמוד *Talmud* of ארץ ישראל *Eretz Yisrael*,
כשהערוד נושך את האדם *kesheh'arod noshech et ha'adam*, if ערוד *arod* bites
the man. אם ערוד קודם למים *im arod kodem lamayim*, if the
ערוד *arod* gets to the water first, מת האדם *met ha'adam*, the
man dies. ואם אדם קודם למים *ve'im adam kodem lamayim*, and if
the man gets to the water first, מת הערוד *met ha'arod*, the
ערוד *arod* dies. That whoever touches water first will determine if the
other one will die. Somehow that's not miraculous, that's natural. Okay, ואם
אדם קודם *ve'im adam kodem* and ונעשה נס לרבי חנינא *vena'aseh nes
le'Rabbi Chanina* ונבקע מעיין מתחת עקבו *venivka ma'ayan mitachat akevo* and him,
a water washed it out, but yeah, it doesn't fully explain it
because it does mean if the ערוד *arod* gets there first, he's
going to die. But anyway, may I don't know, anyway רש"י *Rashi*
tries to make it a little more natural. It's like the it's
like the joke that these talk about חסידים *Chassidim*, these חסידים *Chassidim*
are comparing how great their רבי *Rebbe* is. So one says, you
know, my רבי *Rebbe* is so great that he can like see
for like two miles.
And the other one
says, my רבי *Rebbe* is so great he can see what's happening
in the next town. That's nothing. My רבי *Rebbe* can stand on
a park bench and see all the way what's happening in China.
He says, why does he have to stand on a park bench?
Because he likes to do his ניסים בדרך הטבע *nissim bederech hateva*.
So alright, so this is בדרך הטבע *bederech hateva*.
It wasn't just that they died, it happened to die because water
opened up beneath him.
Anyway, תוספות *Tosafot* says like this. תוספות *Tosafot* says again, תוספות *Tosafot*
again qualifies this issue about, you know, not being so reckless with
your life. If you look at תוספות *Tosafot*, על עקרב פוסק *al
akrav posek*, it says בירושלמי קאמר *bi'Yerushalmi ka'amar*, אם היה נחש מרתיע
לבוא כנגדו *im haya nachash martia lavo kenegdo*, if the snake was
looking like it's sort of like prepared to attack you, פוסק *posek*,
then you better interrupt. ולפי שבבוא כנגדו בכעס *ulifi shebevo kenegdo becha'as*
מתכוון להזיק *mitkaven lehazik*. Okay, and then he discusses whether if you
do interrupt, do you go back to the beginning of שמנה עשרה
*Shmoneh Esrei* or do you go back to where you interrupted and
so on. So obviously there's a reasonable distinction here between, you know,
whether there's a real risk to yourself or not. But nevertheless, the
message is very clear that you're not just, you know, saying a
ברכה *bracha* or saying שמע *Shema*, you're standing in God's presence and
that has to be the mindset. And that might be again why
it's put juxtaposed to the earlier משניות *Mishnayot*, which is all about
creating the right mindset in דאווענינג *davening*, about how one has כוונה
*kavanah* and the חסידים *Chassidim* have the כוונה *kavanah*, and then it
talks about, you know, that you have to really see yourself as
standing before God and here's a way in which it plays out.
Okay, now we turn from that heavy emphasis on כוונה *kavanah* to
a discussion about the text of תפילה *tefillah*. And this next משנה
*Mishnah* is exact appears exactly in תענית *Ta'anit* because it discusses תענית
*Ta'anit* is all about fast days for rain, so the beginning of
מסכת תענית *Masechet Ta'anit* discusses the way we insert what we insert
in our prayers for rain on a regular basis. So let's take
a look. מזכירין גבורות גשמים בתחיית המתים *Mazkirin gevurot geshamim bit'chiyat hametim*.
You mention the power of rain in the ברכה *bracha* of the
resurrection of the dead, right? משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם *Mashiv haruach umorid
hagashem*. ושאלה בברכת השנים *Veshe'elah bevirchat hashanim*. And you ask for rain,
ותן טל ומטר לברכה *veten tal umatar livracha* in the blessing of
the years, of when you sort of say the ninth ברכה *bracha*
where you ask for a prosperous year. והבדלה *Ve'havdalah*, where do you
mention הבדלה *Havdalah*? בחונן הדעת *Be'chonen hada'at*. That in the ברכה *bracha*
of בחונן הדעת *chonen hada'at*, of intelligence, which is the first of
the middle ברכות *brachot* of God giving us intellect. רבי עקיבא אומר
אומרה ברכה רביעית בפני עצמה *Rabbi Akiva omer omrah bracha revi'it bifnei
atzmah*. No, הבדלה *Havdalah* gets a separate ברכה *bracha*. It's a separate
it's the fourth ברכה *bracha*, it's meaning of the שמנה עשרה *Shmoneh
Esrei* before you even get to בחונן הדעת *chonen hada'at*. רבי אליעזר
אומר בהודאה *Rabbi Eliezer omer be'hoda'ah*, you wait for מודים *Modim*. So
interestingly by הבדלה *Havdalah* there was no obvious place for it to
go, so there's a range of opinions of where it would go.
Okay, let's see the גמרא *Gemara*. מזכירין גבורות גשמים מאי טעמא *Mazkirin
gevurot geshamim mai ta'ama*, why do we mention it in בתחיית המתים
*bit'chiyat hametim*? So אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef* מתוך ששקולה כתחיית
המתים *mitoch sheshkulah kitechiyas hameisim* because it's as weighty as the resurrection
of the dead because it so לפיכך קבעוה בתחיית המתים *lefichach kavoah
b'techiyas hameisim*. Therefore they put it in the פסוק *pasuk* about the
resurrection of the dead. Presumably it's as weighty because people's lives are
dependent on it on a very regular basis. So therefore it's in
the ברכה *brachah* of תחיית המתים *techiyas hameisim*. Now there's other reasons
as well because first of all the whole idea of rain and
of the crops is very much a metaphor for תחיית המתים *techiyas
hameisim*. If you think about it, you put a seed in the
ground like you bury somebody, it decays, it wastes away, and then
rain comes and then a new life comes out. So there's a
whole powerful metaphor of the idea of the rain coming and bringing
life for the תחיית המתים *techiyas hameisim*. The other point as well
to mention is
that the whole תחיית המתים *techiyas hameisim* here is embedded with other
things. If you look in the whole ברכה *brachah* even besides משיב
הרוח ומוריד הגשם *mashiv haruach umorid hagashem*, מכלכל חיים בחסד *mechalkeil chayim
b'chesed*, you sustain life, מחיה מתים ברחמים רבים *mechayeh meisim b'rachamim rabim*,
סומך נופלים ורופא חולים ומתיר אסורים ומקיים אמונתו לישני עפר *someich noflim
v'rofei cholim umatir asurim umkayeim emunato lisheinei afar*. So there's all the
sort of regular ways in which God sustains life and then there's
also מחיה מתים *mechayeh meisim* as well as the ultimate that God
will bring the dead to life. But the משיב הרוח ומוריד הגשם
*mashiv haruach umorid hagashem* certainly fits in with all these ways in
which God sustains life, סומך נופלים *someich noflim*, רופא חולים *rofei cholim*,
מתיר אסורים *matir asurim*. So that's why the whole ברכה *brachah* is
about תחיית המתים *techiyas hameisim*. Okay. מלך ממית ומחיה ומצמיח ישועה *Melech
meimit u'mechayeh umatzmiach yeshuah*, the whole phrase of מצמיח *matzmiach*, צמח *tzemach*,
so the ממית ומחיה *meimit u'mechayeh* there's a very intertwining here with
that with sort of the general way in which God sustains life
and in which sort of the growth from the ground which also
serves as this sort of powerful metaphor for תחיית המתים *techiyas hameisim*.
So human was sprouted from the ground in בראשית ב *Bereishit Bet*.
That's true as well exactly. And there was the coming up from
the dirt and the rain actually that's a point, the rain comes
down and then from that rain God makes human beings. So there's
a lot in which it's not just its equal weight, but it
very much is the theme here of the ברכה *brachah* of תחיית
המתים *techiyas hameisim*. Okay, which is why the ברכה *brachah* of תחיית
המתים *techiyas hameisim* is often called גבורות *Gevurot*. It's not just called,
it's not just about תחיית המתים *techiyas hameisim*, it's about God's power
and God's power to give and sustain life. Okay. So now the
גמרא *Gemara* says ושאילה בברכת השנים מאי טעמא *v'sheilah bivirkas hashanim mai
taama*, why do we say ותן טל ומטר *ten tal umatar* in
the ברכה *brachah* for the prosperous years? So that's an obvious answer.
אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef* מתוך שהיא פרנסה קבעוה בברכת פרנסה
*mitoch shehi parnasah kavoah bivirkas parnasah* because we need rain as a
way of for פרנסה *parnasah*, for our sustenance and therefore that's what
this ברכה *brachah* is about. Okay. הבדלה בחונן הדעת מאי טעמא *Havdalah
b'chonein hadaas mai taama*, why is הבדלה *havdalah* in the ברכה *brachah*
about knowledge, intellect? אמר רב יוסף *Amar Rav Yosef* מתוך שהיא חכמה
קבעוה בברכת חכמה *mitoch shehi chochmah kavoah bivirkas chochmah* because in order
to distinguish is an issue of intellect and therefore they brought it
in the ברכה *brachah* of intellect.
If you think about it,
what does God do when God creates the world? It's God separates,
he's מבדיל *mavdil*, between the water and the heavens and the water
and the ground, and he calls it וירא כי טוב *vayera ki
tov*, the whole sense of distinguishing and separating and assessing, when the
תורה *Torah* speaks about what the כהנים *Kohanim* have to do and
that they can't be drunk and their primary role להורות את בני
ישראל *l'horot et b'nei Yisrael* it's להבדיל בין הקודש ובין החול ובין
הטמא ובין הטהור *l'havdil bein hakodesh u'bein hachol u'bein hatamei u'bein hatahor*
to make distinctions is one of the primary functions of the intellect,
to think and assess, this is קודש *kodesh*, this is חול chol.
*chol*. So therefore that goes right in the ברכה *brachah* of דעת
*daas*. So where was it? רבנן אמרי *Rabbanan amri* the Rabbis say
מתוך שהוא חול *mitoch shehu chol* because it is about weekday issues,
it's about מבדיל בין קודש לחול *mavdil bein kodesh l'chol*, we're into
the weekday, ולפיכך קבעוה בברכת חול *u'vichach kavoah bivirkas chol* they waited
till the fourth ברכה *brachah* which is the ברכה *brachah* you make
during the weekday. The first three ברכות *brachot* you make on שבת
*Shabbat* but the fourth ברכה *brachah* of חונן הדעת *chonein hadaas* you
wait, you make in the weekday. Now the גר"א *Gra* points out
that this is why there's a debate where you put this. Does
it start the ברכה *brachah* of חונן הדעת *chonein hadaas*, does it
come in the middle? The גר"א *Gra* says we do it in
a way that satisfies both of these positions. We first say אתה
חוננתנו לאדם דעת ומלמד לאנוש בינה *atah chonantanu l'adam daas u'malamed le'enosh
binah* which sort of puts it in the framework of the ברכה
*brachah* of חכמה *chochmah*, we mention God gives us intellect, and then
we say מבדיל בין קודש לחול *mavdil bein kodesh l'chol*, and then
we end
with we end with the ברכה *brachah*. Why? Because the end of
the ברכה *brachah* we're already making a בקשה bakasha *bakashah*. By the
end of the ברכה *brachah* we're already saying what is it אתה
חוננתנו ומלמד לאנוש חננו מאתך דעה בינה והשכל *atah chonantanu u'malamed le'enosh
choneinu mei'itcha dei'ah binah v'haskeil*, give us from You, it's a request.
So you don't start requesting until you've declared that it's no longer
שבת *Shabbat*. You don't make requests on שבת *Shabbat*. So you first
have to say המבדיל בין קודש לחול *hamavdil bein kodesh l'chol* before
you say חננו מאתך *choneinu mei'itcha*, you make the personal request. But
you don't start with that because you want it to be embedded
in the ברכה *brachah* of דעת *daas*, so you start with אתה
חוננתנו *atah chonantanu*. So he says that's exactly why we do it
that way. So it's framed with the idea that this is about
דעת, but it comes before we actually make a בקשה until only
after we've declared it to be חול. Okay, so I guess we'll
end here and pick up after דף. daf.